בוקר טוב *Boker tov*, today's דף *daf* is צ"ג *Tzaddik Gimmel* but
we are behind and we pick up on the top of צ"ב
עמוד ב' *Tzaddik Beis Amud Beis*, צ"ב עמוד ב' *Tzaddik Beis Amud
Beis* and we're dealing with רבא Rava *Rava* asking רבה בר מרי
Rabba bar Mari, *Rabba bar Mari* where the basis is in the
תורה Torah. *Torah* or in rabbinic literature for common popular sayings. So
we pick up in the צ"ב עמוד ב' *Tzaddik Beis Amud Beis*
and we are אמר ליה רבא לרבה בר מרי Ama lei Rava
l'Rabba bar Mari, *Amlei
Rava le-Rabba bar Mari* it's about fifteen lines down, line starts with
the word מרי *Mari*. Okay, מנא הא מילתא דאמרי milsa d'amri רבנן
Rabbanan, *Mina ha-milsa de-amri rabbanan* where is the basis for this thing
that the rabbis say, that the rabbis say מנא הא מילתא דאמרי
רבנן *Mina ha-milsa de-amri rabbanan*, חברך קרייך חמרא אוכפא לגבך מוש *Chavrach
karcha chamra uchva legabach mosh*, if your friend called you a donkey,
then put the saddle on your own back, meaning be willing I
guess to tolerate the insult and put the saddle on your own
back rather than to, you know, fight it or something. Not that
you should degrade yourself, but maybe that's just the, you know, don't
you don't always have to fight these things makes makes life harder.
Let's anyway look at the example. אמר ליה דכתיב Ama lei dechsav,
*Amlei d'chsiv*, okay, so again צ"ב עמוד ב' *Tzaddik Beis Amud Beis*
we're quoting from the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* ויאמר *Vayomer* about fifteen twenty
lines down, דכתיב Dechsav, ויאמר הגר Hagar. שפחת שרי אי מזה באת
ואנה תלכי *de-chsiv Vayomer Hagar shifchat Sarai ay mi-zeh bat ve-ana telechi*,
the angel said to הגר *Hagar*, the maidservant of שרה Sarah, *Sarah*,
ויאמר *Vayomer* and he said, excuse me, הגר שפחת שרי אי מזה
באת ואנה תלכי *Hagar shifchat Sarai ay mi-zeh bat ve-ana telechi*, Hagar
maidservant of Sarah, where are you coming from, where are you going?
ותאמר מפני שרי גברתי אנכי ברחת *Vatomer mipnei Sarai gevirti anochi borachat*,
she said I'm running away from Sarah my master, mistress I guess.
So anyway, so the point is that she was no longer שפחת
שרי *shifchat Sarai*, she was running away, or maybe she wasn't so
much שפחת שרי *shifchat Sarai* because she was given the role of
being a concubine of אברהם Avraham *Avraham*. And nevertheless, the angel called
her that and she accepted that, you know, that name rather than
fighting it.
Okay. אמר ליה רבא לרבה בר מרי Ama lei Rava l'Rabba bar
Mari, מנא הא מילתא דאמרי אינשי mena ha milta de-amri inshi, *Amlei
Rava le-Rabba bar Mari mina ha-milsa de-amri inshi*, where is this thing
that people say, מילתא גנאה דאית בך *milsa gina'a de-is bach*, if
there now that thing wasn't exactly accurate, but she was willing to
repeat it rather than to fight it. But how do you know
if there actually is something unseemly that you have that's about you,
קדים אמרה *kadem amra*, that you should be the one to put
it out there and say it first, you know, rather than wait
for somebody else to accuse you of it and to discover it.
דאמר *de-amar* so where's that from? אמר ליה דכתיב Amar lei dikhtiv,
ויאמר עבד אברהם אנכי *Amlei d'chsiv Vayomer Eved Avraham anochi*. So אברהם'ס
*Avraham's* servant went, you know, to marry off יצחק Yitzchak, *Yitzchak*, just
right outside I'm a slave, right? He didn't try to claim that
he was like an agent of אברהם *Avraham* and let them discover
that he was a slave. אמר ליה רבא לרבה בר מרי Ama
lei Rava l'Rabba bar Mari, מנא הא מילתא דאמרי אינשי mena ha
milta de-amri inshi, *Amlei Rava le-Rabba bar Mari mina ha-milsa de-amri inshi*,
where is this thing from that the popular saying שפיל ואזיל בר
אווזא ועינוהי מטייפי *shafil ve-azil bar avza ve-einei mitayfe*, the duck goes
with its eyes down,
but its eyes look far into the distance, even if you're lowly
you could have you could or you should have high aspirations. אמר
ליה דכתיב Amar lei dikhtiv, *Amlei d'chsiv* the verse says והיטיב השם
לאדוני *ve-heitiv Hashem la-adoni*, this is by אביגיל *Avigail* where she was
still married there and while and, you know, and she said to
דוד *Dovid* so that, you know, that נבל *Naval* her husband was
alive, but she said to דוד *Dovid* God should do good to
my master meaning you דוד *Dovid* meaning David, וזכרת את אמתך *ve-zacharta
es amasecha* and remember your maidservant, meaning like so here she still
was the, you know, subjugated wife of נבל *Naval*, but she was
had her aspirations about what might happen in the future. Okay. אמר
ליה רבא amar leh Rava לרבה בר מרי *Amlei Rava le-Rabba bar
Mari* good thing?
What? That's considered a good thing?
Well, I mean, like she's thinking.
Yeah, I understand.
Well, she was married to a creep, but anyway, not to worry
about
a degenerate.
I know it's not clear if this saying is that it's a
fact that even lowly people have high aspirations or it's a recommendation.
Okay. אמר ליה Amar lei, רבא Rava לרבה בר מרי מנא הא
מילתא דאמרי אינשי mena ha milta de-amri inshi, *Amlei Rava le-Rabba bar
Mari mina ha-milsa de-amri inshi*, where is this basis of this thing
that people say ששין תכלי מטייה לככא דקל חבריה שמע *shishin tichli
matiya le-kachaka de-kal chavrei shama*, you see again, some of this is
just descriptive rather than prescriptive. Sixty illnesses affect the teeth of somebody
who hears his friend eating. Okay, somebody's eating and you're not, right,
you know, you feel it, like, you know, you get there's this
jealousy. Okay, and you feel, so אמר ליה דכתיב amar lei de-chtiv,
*Amlei d'chsiv* because the verse says בי לי אני עבדך ולצדוק הכהן
ולבניהו בן יהוידע ולשלמה עבדך לא lo, קרא *bi li ani avdecha
u-le-Tzadok ha-kohen u-le-Vnayahu ben Yehoyada u-le-Shlomo avdecha lo kara*, that you know,
your son אדוניה *Adoniyah* is saying that he's going to be the
king and he's and he made this whole feast and he didn't
invite me to the meal. So obviously he was feeling very upset.
Obviously the point wasn't that you didn't get to eat the nice
smorg, but anyway, but that's how it's being read. Oh, you know,
how come I didn't get to eat part of that smorg? אמר
ליה Amar lei, איהו מהתם ואנא אמינא מהכא *Amlei ihu me-hasam va-ana
amina me-hacha*, you say from there and I say from here. ויביאה
יצחק Yitzchak, האהלה שרה אמו *Vayavi'eha Yitzchak ha-ohela Sarai imo*, יצחק Yitzchak
*Yitzchak* brought his her to his, you know, רבקה Rivka, *Rivka* to
his tent to the tent of שרה *Sarah* his mother, ויקח את
רבקה ותהי לו לאשה ויאהבה וינחם יצחק אחרי אמו *vayikach es Rivka
va-tehi lo le-ishah va-ye'ehaveha vayinachem Yitzchak acharei imo*, he was consoled, וכתב
בתריה *u-chsiv basrei* and what do we read immediately afterwards? ויוסף אברהם
ויקח אשה ושמה קטורה *Vayosef Avraham vayikach isha u-shma Keturah*, אברהם *Avraham*
got married. He saw his son was married, he wasn't, he he
felt that and he acted on it and therefore he he got
married again. Okay. אמר ליה amar lei רבא Rava לרבה בר מרי
*Amlei Rava le-Rabba bar Mari* And he took רבקה and she became
his wife and he loved her, and he was consoled, יצחק, after
his mother. וכתיב וינחם יצחק אחרי אמו, Uchsiv vayanchom Yitzchak acharei imo,
he was consoled. וכתיב בתריה, Uchsiv basrei, what do we read immediately
afterwards? ויסף אברהם ויקח אשה ושמה קטורה. Vayosaf Avraham vayikach isha u'shma
Ketura. אברהם got married. He saw his son was married, he wasn't,
he felt that and he acted on it and therefore he got
married again. Okay. אמר ליה רבא לרבה בר מרי, רבא said to
רבה בר מרי, מניין הא דאמרי אינשי, Minayin ha de'amrei inshi, where
is this thing that people say, חמרא למרי טיבותא לשקיא, Chamra l'mari
tivuta l'shakya, that the wine belongs to the owner, but the gratitude
is given to the wine steward, to the waiter, to the guy
who's pouring the wine, okay. אמר ליה דכתיב, dechsav,
because the verse says, וסמכת את ידך עליו, V'samachta es yadcha alav,
by משה Moshe and יהושע, Yehoshua, put your hand on him. למען
ישמעו וייראו כל עדת בני ישראל, L'maan yishmeu v'yireu kol adat bnei
Yisrael, that all the people of Israel will hear and will see.
וכתיב ויהושע בן נון מלא רוח חכמה, Uchsiv V'Yehoshua bin Nun malei
ruach chochma, he was filled with wisdom. כי סמך משה את ידיו
עליו, Ki samach Moshe es yadav alav, because משה Moshe put his
hands on him. וישמעו אליו כל בני ישראל, Vayishmeu elav kol bnei
Yisrael, and they listened to him. So it says that the actually
the פסוק pasuk here ascribes it that it's because of what משה
Moshe did, even though really the divine רוח ruach is coming from
God, משה Moshe was just as it were the conveyer, the vehicle,
the כלי kli through which that רוח ruach was being given. Nevertheless,
the פסוק pasuk doesn't say because of God's spirit rested on him,
it's because משה Moshe put his hands on him. תוספות Tosafos says
a different version of this. תוספות Tosafos says that God says, he
says, even if the wine belongs to the owner, it's the guy
who's pouring the wine that gets to decide how much to give
you. So God says to משה, Moshe, put your hand in the
singular on יהושע, Yehoshua, and it says משה Moshe put his hands
on יהושע. Yehoshua. So anyway, this is why you should be nice
to your waiter. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: אמר ליה רבא
לרבה בר מרי, מניין הא דאמרי אינשי, Minayin ha de'amrei inshi,
where's this base where this things people say: כלבא בכפנא גללי מבלע,
Kalba bechafnai galali mivla,
a dog when it's starving will even swallow its eat its own
excrement. דכתיב, or actually it says it'll eat rocks. Anyway, נפש שבעה
תבוס נופת, Nefesh sveia tavus nofes, a satisfied, a sated soul
will refuse honey, ונפש רעבה כל מר מתוק, V'nefesh reiva kol mar
matok, and a hungry soul, anything bitter tastes sweet. All right. אמר
ליה רבא לרבה בר מרי, not everything here is most profound, but
okay, these are popular sayings that ultimately it's more of making a
statement like everything is in the תורה. Torah. Even the popular wisdom
can be found in the תורה. Torah מניין הא דאמרי אינשי, Minayin
ha de'amrei inshi, where's this thing people say: מטייל ואזל דיקלא בישא
גבי קינא דסרכי, Metayel v'azal dikla bisha gabei kina d'sarchi,
a bad tree goes and it and it moves itself towards the
place where there are these where there are barren trees or a
barren field of barren trees. אמר ליה, דבר זה כתוב בתורה שנוי
בנביאים ומשולש בכתובים. Davar ze kasuv baTorah shanuy baNeviim u'meshulash baKesuvim. Birds
of a
feather flock together? No, more like
evil attracts evil, bad attracts bad. Bad people will go to where
there's others of his kind.
I'm sorry? One tree with Dutch elm disease. That's like a bad
apple will spoil the bunch, but this is different. This is not
you're part of a group and you're bad and you spoil the
group. It's like somebody bad will seek out others of his kind.
Anyway, let's take a look at the example, okay. דבר זה כתוב
בתורה שנוי בנביאים ומשולש בכתובים. Davar ze kasuv baTorah shanuy baNeviim u'meshulash
baKesuvim. תנן במתניתין, Tnan b'matnisin, and it's taught in a משנה, Mishnah,
ותנינא בברייתא, u'tanina b'braisa,
so we got it in all of תורה and Rabbinic literature. כתוב
בתורה: Kasuv baTorah: דכתיב וילך עשו אל ישמעאל, Dechsav vayelech Esav el
Yishmael, okay, עשו Esav went to ישמעאל. Yishmael. So, you know, the
bad tree went to the other bad tree, the barren tree.
Now by the way,
I just want to put this out there, I mean although it
obviously goes against our sensibilities, but the מהרש״א Maharsha says that the
idea here is also like you know we say coming from good
stock? So the מהרש״א Maharsha says actually the idea of bad tree
versus barren tree is that the bad tree comes from good stock
but it produces bad fruit. And the barren tree is the one
that comes from bad stock. So עשו Esav came straight from יצחק,
right? You know from יצחק and רבקה, he came from good stock
but he produced bad fruit. And he went to ישמעאל Yishmael who
came from bad stock because his mother was הגר. Okay, and that's
how he like reads these, actually it's a very nice that you
know connects with this idea of a bad tree as opposed to
a barren tree. All
right. וילך עשו אל ישמעאל. Vayelech Esav el Yishmael. שנוי בנביאים, Shanuy
baNeviim, דכתיב ויתלקטו אל יפתח אנשים ריקים, Dechsav vayislaksu el Yiftach anashim
reikim, so you know these worthless or you know lowly people gathered
to יפתח, Yiftach, but if you remember יפתח Yiftach was also the
son of a prostitute woman, exactly. So the מהרש״א Maharsha's read is
a very insightful read. והיו עמו, V'hayu imo, and they were with
him, or וייצאו עמו. v'yeitziu imo. ומשולש בכתובים, U'meshulash baKesuvim, it says
a third time in the כתובים: Kesuvim: דכתיב כל עוף למינו ישכון,
Dechsav kol of l'mino yishkon, every bird will dwell amongst its kind,
ובני אדם לדומה לו, u'vnei adam l'domeh lo, and people to those
that are similar to it. If that does not sound to you
as any פסוק pasuk you've ever heard, it's because it is written
in בן סירא. Ben Sira. So very interesting that although you know
we read in the משנה Mishnah in סנהדרין Sanhedrin that הקורא בספרים
חיצוניים ואין לו חלק לעולם הבא, Hakoray b'sfarim chitzoniyim v'ein lo chelek
l'olam haba, חז״ל Chazal certainly were very familiar with בן סירא Ben
Sira and would quote it often, and every now and then they
even quote it as saying דכתיב, as if it's Scripture, and here
it
says משולש בכתובים. meshulash baKesuvim. Whatever, I'm not having that discussion. תנן
במתניתין: Tnan b'matnisin: כל המחובר לטמא טמא כל המחובר לטהור טהור. Kol
hamuchbar l'tamei tamei kol hamuchbar l'tahor tahor. Here you're losing the idea
of the stock idea. Anything connected to something טמא tamei is טמא,
tamei, connected something טהור tahor is טהור. tahor. The idea is you
take a nail, a metal thing, a metal utensil is מקבל טומאה.
mekabel tumah. But if you bang a nail into a type of
a wooden utensil that it does not have a בית קיבול, beit
kibbul, does not have a receptacle, I see your your eyes picked
up. Anyway a wooden a wooden a sort of instrument without a
receptacle is not מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. So let's say you banged
a nail into I don't know, let's say you have a wood
stick to stir, to stir your soup and you banged a nail
into it so you could hang it on a hook, okay? Then
even the nail is no longer מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah because it's
מחובר לטהור. mehubar le-tahor. So if you however banged it into something
that was טמא, tamei, if you banged let's say a wooden nail
into something that was טמא, tamei, something that was מקבל טומאה, mekabel
tumah, like a metal utensil, it would be part of that metal
utensil and the wood would be מקבל טומאה. mekabel tumah. So anyway
something connected to טהור tahor is טהור, tahor, something connected to טמא
tamei is טמא, tamei,
which isn't exactly the same point. Anyway, ותנינא בברייתא, ve-tanina be-vrayta, and
we taught again in the ברייתא, vrayta, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabi Eliezer
omer, לא לחינם הלך זרזיר אצל עורב. lo le-hinam halakh zarzir etzel
oreiv. There was a question whether this bird זרזיר, zarzir, I think
they say it was a starling, is כשר kosher or not. And
he said it's not for naught that it goes and it it
flocks together with the with the raven, אלא מפני שהוא מינו, ela
mipenei she-hu mino, it's of its same species and therefore it is
it is not a כשר kosher bird. So these last things were
again the מהרש"א's Maharsha idea wasn't the same, but anyway it's bad
attracts bad. Okay.
אמר ליה רבא לרב בר מרי, Amar lei Rava le-Rav bar Mari,
מנא הא מילתא דאמרי אינשי, mena ha milta de-amri inshi, where is
this thing that people say, קרי
ליה לחברך ולא ענך, kari leih le-havrakh ve-la anakh, if you called
your friend and he didn't respond to you, and it seems for
the context it's not just
hey חיים Chaim how you doing, but it means you tried to
warn him about something and he ignored you, so רמי גודא רבא
שדי ביה, remi guda raba shady beih, basically take a big wall
and throw it on him. If he's not listening to your warnings,
to hell with him, excuse me. אמר ליה,
יען טהרתיך ולא טהרת, yaan tihara-tikha ve-lo taharta, since I tried to
purify you and you would not become pure, מטומאתך לא תטהרי עוד,
mi-tumatekha lo tithari od, from your impurity I will no longer you
will no longer become pure.
That's not actively doing it, right? I know, I know. So it's
not exactly the same, you can't imagine that you would actually think
you would actively try to hurt somebody. We had that before actually,
remember about the צנועים tznuim would put out these warnings about people
גנבים ganavim coming into the field that they shouldn't eat the ערלה
orlah and whatever and the כלאים kilayim and so on and who
was it somebody said what was the פסוק pasuk somebody said about
that? He said
something about let them eat and die? Yeah, right, right, right. I'm
trying to remember the פסוק pasuk, though. What was it? Anyway, basically
said a similar type of a sentiment
about they're גנבים ganavim anyway, whatever, why do you have to care
about that?
Okay.
אמר ליה רבא לרב בר מרי, Amar lei Rava le-Rav bar Mari,
מנא הא מילתא דאמרי אינשי, mina ha milta de-amri inshi? בירא דשתית
מיניה לא תשדי ביה קלא, beira de-shatit mineih la tishdei beih kala,
the well that you drank from don't throw in it clods of
earth into it. Something that you got benefit from even if now
it's dried up or whatever, don't go ahead and disrespect it. אמר
ליה דכתיב, לא תתעב אדומי כי אחיך הוא ולא תתעב מצרי כי
גר היית בארצו. lo titaev Adomi ki akhikha hu ve-lo titaev Mitzri
ki ger hayita be-artzo. Here do not despise the אדומי, Adomi, you're
your brother, and don't despise the מצרי, Mitzri, you were a sojourner
in their land even after all the evil that they did to
you, I mean even the אדומי Adomi they wouldn't let them pass
through the land, the מצרי Mitzri of course, nevertheless you have to
still have a certain amount of הכרת הטוב hakarat ha-tov of gratitude
even if the facts changed afterwards.
אמר ליה רבא לרב בר מרי, Amar lei Rava le-Rav bar Mari,
מנא הא מילתא דאמרי אינשי, אי דלי פדלי דלינא, i dali padli
dalina, if you carry the
beam, or the excuse me the burden, then I will carry it
with you, ואי לא לא דלינא, ve-i lo lo dalina, but if
you won't I won't carry it, meaning if you do it I'll
do it with you, okay, but I can't do it by I
won't do it by myself. אמר ליה דכתיב, ויאמר אליה ברק, va-yomer
eleiha Barak,
ברק Barak said to דבורה, Devorah, אם תלכי עמי והלכתי ואם לא
תלכי עמי לא אלך. im telkhi imi ve-halakhti ve-im lo telkhi imi
lo elekh. Okay,
if you go with me I'll go, if not I won't. אמר
ליה רבא לרב בר מרי, Amar lei Rava le-Rav bar Mari, מנא
הא מילתא דאמרי אינשי, כד הוינא
זוטרי לגברי, kad havina zutrei le-gavrei, when we were young לגברי, le-gavrei,
so we were we saw ourselves
as real
powerful,
when we were young we thought ourselves like we were adults, והשתא
דקשישנא לדרדקי, ve-hashta de-kashishna le-dardekei, and now that we've gotten old לדרדקי,
le-dardekei, now we're like children, because the old become infirm and they
need other and they need people to take care of them. So
we've reverted to children. When we were children we thought we were
adults and now that we're old we're back to being children. אמר
ליה מעיקרא כתיב, Amar lei me-ikara ketiv, וה' הולך לפניהם יומם בעמוד
ענן לנחותם הדרך, ve-Adonai holekh lifneihem yomam be-amud anan le-nahotam ha-derekh, God
led them with a pillar of smoke, ובלילה בעמוד אש להאיר להם.
u-ve-layla be-amud esh le-hair lahem. So I don't know if maybe the
idea here about being like גברי gavrei adults or fully empowered is
that God is showing them the way but they are going, it's
not like God is leading. is, you know, God, you know, God
is pointing them the way, but ultimately, you know, they're empowered, right?
As opposed to ובסוף כתיב הנה אנכי שולח מלאך לפניך לשמרך בדרך.
u-vasof ketiv hineh anochi sholeach malach lefanecha lishmorcha baderech. I'll send my
angel, he'll take care of you. Right? Taking care of somebody is
of a very—it's like more infantilizing. All right. אמר ליה רבה לרב
בר מרי, amar lei Rabbah le-Rav bar Mari, top of צג עמוד
א, tzadik gimmel amud aleph, מנא הא מילתא דאמרי אינשי? Where is
this thing that people say? בתר מרי נכסי צבי משך. batar marei
nichsei tzevi mashach. After the person of wealth, the wood chips follow,
you know, like, so
you know, like hang out with—hang
out with what they said, בתר עניא אזל עניותא. batar anya azal
anyuta.
Yeah, exactly.
Exactly. That's the poor get poorer, right? But this is actually follow
the rich and you'll benefit from being in their ambit essentially. Okay.
אמר ליה דכתיב, וגם ללוט ההלך את אברם היה צאן ובקר ואהלים.
ve-gam le-Lot ha-holech et Avram hayah tzon u-vakar ve-ohalim. Look, Lot with
Avram, he had all this good stuff. אמר רב חנן. amar Rav
Chanan. Okay, now we're going to shift a little bit back because
we were talking about, a lot of this was about talking about
Avraham and Sarah and so on, we're done with popular sayings and
a little bit more דרשות drashot about Avraham and Sarah and related
things. So let's take a look.
אמר רב
חנן המוסר דין על חבירו. amar Rav Chanan ha-moser din al chaveiro.
Somebody who gives over to Heaven, like, the judgment about somebody, he
says, you know, God should judge you, you know, let God be
the judge, okay, I want God to mete out judgment against you.
הוא נענש תחילה. hu ne'enash techila. You're the one that—you're asking God
to come and pay attention and to judge, God will first check
out, you know, your doings, and you'll be the one to be
punished first for anything you've done wrong. שנאמר ותאמר שרי אל אברם
חמסי עליך. shene'emar vatomer Sarai el Avram chamasi alecha. Sarai said to
Avraham, my anger is upon you, or the injury done to me
is upon you, you know, ישפט ה' ביני וביניך. yishpot Hashem beini
u-veinecha. That's the key, the end of the פסוק, pasuk, God should
judge between us. וכתיב ויבא אברהם לספוד לשרה ולבכתה. u-chtiv vayavo Avraham
lispod le-Sarah ve-livkota. Who was the one that died first? It was
Sarah who died first. So that's much later. So, okay, it doesn't
mean it's going to be immediate. Okay, but you bring God into
it, you know, God is going to first check that you were
worthy of calling God to judge this. והני מילי דאית ליה דינא
בארעא. ve-hanei milei de-it lei dina be-ar'a. But that's only if you
had other recourse. If you could have, you know, you could have
brought somebody to a בית דין, beit din, you could have brought
them to court, and therefore you didn't, you brought God into it
instead, then God's going to be looking more closely at you. Of
course, the מהרש"א Maharsha said, or somebody said, where did, what do
you call it, you know, where did Sarah have a בית דין?
beit din? Well, there was always the בית דין beit din of
שם, Shem, so there you go.
Okay, what can I tell you?
To be adjudicated. What can I tell you? והני מילי—well, ve-hanei milei
I don't know, I don't know what to say about that. והני
מילי דאית ליה... ve-hanei milei de-it lei... okay. אמר רבי יצחק, amar
Rabbi Yitzchak, אוי לו לצועק יותר מן הנצעק. oi lo la-tzo'ek yoter
min ha-nitza'ak. Similar idea. Woe is to the one who cries out
to God more than the one who is being called out about.
Okay? Same idea. Somebody is complaining to you about God, that person
has to more worry about themselves. How do you know? תניא נמי
הכי, tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly, הצועק—which is not more, but
at least
equal—אחד הצועק ואחד הנצעק echad ha-tzo'ek ve-echad ha-nitza'ak, במשמע. Oh, and it
is
more, because רש"י Rashi quotes the פסוק, pasuk? it says, it says,
where is רש"י? Rashi?
וחרה אפי והרגתי אתכם בחרב. ve-charah api ve-haragti etchem be-charev. Okay, it
says that you know, if you—I forget, what's the beginning of the
פסוק? pasuk, והיה כי יצעק אלי—no, ve-hayah ki yitz'ak elai no, no.
כל אלמנה ויתום לא תענון. kol almanah ve-yatom lo te'annun.
That's the end of it. What's the beginning? No, וחרה אפי, ve-charah
api, no, but who's calling out to God? I forgot. Anyway, somebody
who's oppressed calls out to God, and God says, my anger will
be kindled against you, and I will kill you, all of you.
I not kill him, the one who did bad to you, but
you, in the plural, בחרב. be-charev. So אחד הצועק ואחד הנצעק, the
one calling and the one being called upon, they are both going
to suffer God's retribution. אלא שממהרים לצועק
יותר מן הנצעק. ella she-memaharim la-tzo'ek yoter min ha-nitza'ak. The one who
called out, he's going to be the one that's going to get
punished first. Okay, so that's pretty interesting, you know, given, I mean,
it's right, directly against the whole point of the פסוק, pasuk like,
what's the idea that, you know, God answers the oppressed? But the
point is, it's one thing, and you know, maybe that's also why
the word לצועק la-tzo'ek is different than המוסר דין, ha-moser din, right?
צועק tzo'ek is not necessarily calling God to judge, right? צועק tzo'ek
is like just crying out because you're oppressed, right? Like by בני
ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, it says, right? It says, ויזעקו, va-yiz'aku,
ותעל שועתם אל הא-להים. va-ta'al shav'atam el ha-Elokim. It's not that they
prayed to God. They were just, you know, crying out because they
were oppressed. God heard it, but it wasn't calling God into it.
And here the גמרא Gemara is saying that even the צועק tzo'ek
is going to be punished. Now, תוספות Tosafot pushes back a little
bit about that, or he quotes a different מדרש. Midrash. And if
you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, ד"ה אחד הצועק ואחד הנצעק.
dibur hamatchil echad ha-tzo'ek ve-echad ha-nitza'ak.
Take a look, he says, אמר רבינו שמואל דבספרי משני בענין אחר.
amar Rabbeinu Shmuel de-ve-Sifrei mishni be-inyan acher. In ספרי Sifrei there's a
different version of this. אחד הצועק ואחד שאין צועק במשמע. echad ha-tzo'ek
ve-echad she-ein tzo'ek be-mashma. Whether you call out or whether you don't
call out, God is going to punish the oppressor. Okay?
So oppressor, right? What does that mean? God is only going to
punish the oppressor if somebody cries out? If not, God won't? So
what's the idea of crying out?
שניהם נענשים shneihem ne'enashim unless מאי טעמא mai ta'ama כיוון שאין מחזיר
עבוטו, keivan she'ein machzir avoto, that was the case, he didn't return
the collateral. זה כמו זה ze kmo ze and God of course
will punish both of them oppressed the person. אלא הכי כתיב ela
hachi kesiv שמוע אשמע צעקתו וחרה אפי shamoa eshma tza'akaso v'charah api
שממהרים לפרוע יותר ממי שאינו צועק. shemema'arim lipro'a yoseir mimi she'eino tzo'eik.
If he calls out, then God will punish the oppressor even faster.
Now that's obviously much more פשט pshat of the פסוקים. psukim. Okay,
that's saying, okay, God is going to respond to the calling out,
but how about God should be protecting the, you know, punishing the
oppressor regardless? He will, but he'll respond even quicker to the one
who calls out. But that's not what the גמרא Gemara is saying.
Right, the גמרא Gemara is saying like, don't call, you know, don't
call God to intervene, which is so funny. I mean, that's the
classic religious response of somebody who's oppressed.
Well, yeah, because you've just got to make sure your house is
in order.
I guess so. Okay, ואמר רבי יצחק v'amar Rabbi Yitzchak לעולם אל
תהי קללת הדיוט קלה בעיניך. le'olam al tehi klalas hedyot kala b'einecha.
So it's very interesting. That was about calling God to intervene, but
if somebody doesn't call on God, somebody just curses you, that's going
to be effective. So if you want to, if you, if you're
having a problem with someone, don't call on God to judge, just
curse the person. So how do you know that the curse of
a, even of a commoner, should not be light in your eyes,
should not be taken lightly? שהרי אבימלך, sheharei Avimelech, we're circling back
to אבימלך, Avimelech, קילל את שרה, kileil es Sarah, he cursed שרה,
ונתקיים בזרעה, v'niskayeim b'zar'ah, and it was actually fulfilled in her in
her seed, in her descendants, שנאמר she'ne'emar הנה הוא לך כסות עיניים.
hinei hu lach ksus einayim. Here I'm giving you this money, it
should be a covering of the eyes. Now presumably what that means
is like a veil, it'll protect you against the shame of this
event. But here's how the גמרא Gemara reads it. פושט, posheit, there
you go. Exactly. Well, that's exactly how our discussion, אף על פי
שהוא נותן לו אינו נמחל. af al pi shehu nosein lo eino
nimchal. That's a good point, I wasn't thinking about the כסות עיניים.
ksus einayim. Anyway, so okay, אמר ליה הואיל וכסית ממני ho'il v'chasis
mimeni you hid from me the truth, ולא גילית שהוא אישך v'lo
gilis shehu isheich and you did not reveal
that he is your husband, וגרמת לי הצער הזה v'gramt li hatza'ar
haze and you caused me all of this anguish, it really is
still you to blame, even though previously God said don't say they're
to blame, you're to blame. Anyway,
יהי רצון yehi ratzon let it be the desire שיהיו לך בני
כסויי עיניים sheyiyu lach bnei kisuyei einayim that your children should have
their eyes covered. Okay, so כסות עיניים ksus einayim is a curse.
You know, you should have your children should have their eyes covered.
See it differently, instead of saying I'm doing something nice for you.
Right, exactly. ונתקיים בזרעה דכתיב v'niskayeim b'zar'ah d'chsiv ויהי כי זקן יצחק
ותכהין עיניו מראות. vayehi ki zakein Yitzchak vatich'hein einav meir'os. His eyes
became hard of seeing, okay, or dim of seeing. אמר רבי אבהו.
amar Rabbi Abbahu. פושט. posheit.
What?
I know. That's a good point, very good, Michael. אמר רבי אבהו
amar Rabbi Abbahu לעולם יהא אדם מן הנרדפים ולא מן הרודפים. le'olam
yehei adam min hanirdaphim v'lo min harodphim. You should always be from
those that are oppressed and not those that are the oppressors. Those
that are being chased rather than the chasers. That's against the Peter,
Paul, and Mary song, right? I'd rather be a hammer than a
nail? Okay,
anyway, שאין לך she'ein lach what? Simon and Gar... that's Simon and
Garfunkel, that's not Peter, Paul, and Mary? Really? Oh, my apologies. You
know how מילתא דאמרי Simon and Garfunkel?
Okay, fine. לעולם יהא מן הנרדפים ולא מן... le'olam yehei min hanirdaphim
v'lo min... no, it's the opposite of מן המילתא. min hamilsa. שאין
לך נרדף בעופות יותר מתורים ובני יונה she'ein lach nirdaph ba'ofos yoseir
miturim uvnei yona because you have you have nothing among the birds
that are more the chased after, the prey, than the turtledoves and
the pigeons, והכשירם הכתוב לגבי מזבח. v'hichshiram hakasuv legabei mizbeiach. And those
are the ones that are the sacrifices. You know, you could have
said the basic general point about the kosher animals versus the non-kosher
animals, right? It's not the predators
are the are the non-kosher. Okay, that was a nice little long
little אגדתא Agadata digression and now we go back to the משנה.
Mishnah. Well look at that, we're almost caught up. Okay, so אוקיי
okay so
כפי
ליה לרושא וימות kefei lei l'rasha v'yamus I think was the פסוק
before, right? Like you know basically feed it to the רשע rasha
and let him die. Anyway, that was the idea of somebody doing
something wrong, you know, then just let them fall in their own
sin. Okay, האומר סמא את עיני ha'omer s'ma es eini now we're
back to the end of the משנה. Mishnah. Somebody says blind me,
even if he says and he says even on the condition that
you'll be פטור patur exempt, you're not פטור. patur. But if he
says tear my garment, if he just says it סתם stam you're
not פטור patur but if he says on the condition that you
will be פטור patur you will. So why does it work for
the garment and not for the eye? So let's take a look
at what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר ליה רב אסי בר חמא
לרבא. amar lei Rav Assi bar Chama l'Rava. So he said to
רבא or to רב, Rav, anyway, מאי שנא רישא ומאי שנא סיפא.
mai shna reisha u'mai shna seifa. Why does exempting a person work
in the case of a garment and not in the case of
a a part of the body? אמר ליה רישא לפי שאין אדם
מוחל על ראשי איברים. amar lei reisha lefi she'ein adam mochal al
rashei evarim. That's obvious, that person, now you could read this "doesn't"
or "can't", okay, but let's read it "doesn't". A person even if
he says he's exempting you, deep down he can never really you
know exempt somebody from injury from an act of injury being done
to him, as opposed to when it comes to vessels, he can
be sincere about it. Okay, now by the way, this does not
mean that after the debt is incurred it cannot that you cannot
have מחילה. mechila. Somebody injured you and they owe you like a
hundred thousand dollars, you could say I'm... Now it's just a monetary
debt. The question is a מחילה *Mechila* beforehand, saying this will be
an act that I will not consider an act of injury to
come with it the liability. I'm going to treat it as if
you're not injuring me. That's what a מחילה *Mechila* beforehand means. You
can't, right, because you can't be מוחל mochel *Mochel* a debt that
doesn't exist. So what does על מנת לפטור al menas liftor, *al
menat liftor* mean? It means I won't consider it like you've done
something wrong to me. So that's why it's possible to read this
statement not just the person doesn't really mean it, but a person
it can't be true. An act of injury to a person's body
is always
objectively an act of injury to somebody. Whereas when you break an
object, that's not a there's a lot of reasons you throw things
out and you break them or what not. Now you could say
sometimes you cut into somebody because you're operating on them. Fine, that
obviously is very clear from not what the person said, but from
the reality of what's happening. Okay, but very often you'll have something
that's functional but you want to make room, you throw it out,
you destroy it. So it's possible to read the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
this way, not like you don't mean it, but because you're being
מוחל mochel *Mochel* before the debt, you're reframing the action. And that's
not possible in the case of personal injury. It is possible in
the case of damaging an object. Okay, so he says לפי שאין
אדם מוחל mochel על ראשי אברים *lefi she'ein adam mochel al rashei
evarim*. אמר ליה *Amar lei*, וכי אדם מוחל על צערו *vechi adam
mochel al tza'aro*? I don't understand, then it shouldn't be limited to
the case of breaking a limb. How could a person be מוחל
*Mochel* on any, even on pain, on being suffered? דתניא detanya. *Detanya*,
we learn in a ברייתא braita. *Baraisa*, הכני פצעני *hakeini pitz'ani*, if
somebody says hit me, you know, wound me, but you're not, you
know, no permanent damage, like the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's* question before, are
you allowed to be חובל בעצמו *chovel be'atzmo*? So not any permanent
damage, על מנת לפטור al menas liftor? *al menat liftor*, on the
condition that you'll be exempt, פטור patur. *patur*, you're exempt. So why
is that true? That also either you shouldn't be sincere about it
according to that way of one way of reading, deep down you
can't really mean it, or the other way of reading, objectively there's
still injury there. Right, so how there does that work more than
the other case? So אשתקי *ishteiki*, he was quiet, he didn't have
an answer. אמר מידי שמיע לך בהא *Amar: midei shmiya lach beha*?
That's a good question. Have you heard any answer to this? So
אמר ליה *amar lei*, הכי אמר רב ששת *hachi amar Rav Sheshes*,
here's what רב ששת *Rav Sheshes* says: משום פגם משפחה pagam mishpacha.
*mishum pgam mishpacha*. It's not the person is sincere, and but there
is injury to the family. And because the family, like somebody suffered
injury, right, you know, somebody's now going around, a member of our
family now is missing a limb or something, you know, that brings
about some some type of a stigma or some type of a
felt injury to the family. Now the question is okay, but you're
not paying the בושת *boshet* to the family, you're paying for the
injury. You know, but apparently what it means is because of that
reality then it seems like it's tied back to the point before
about there's an objective injury. So if somebody gets a wound and
it heals, so to some degree you could say if
there's nothing
permanent, there's no objective injury. But if
somebody it's permanent, so it is objective, whatever the guy says, because
it's felt by others. Okay, it's felt by the family. But it
is funny, their embarrassment means you have to pay full damages. But
it seems what we're saying is the fact of their embarrassment is
a measure to the fact that there is objective injury here and
the person's subjective framing of it as it doesn't mean anything, I
don't care, I don't see it as injury, you know, there's still
the objective reality that you can't change. Yes.
Isn't it only בושת *boshet*?
No, that's my point. Exactly. Exactly. And if you take a look,
look at the one word of the תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*, משום פגם
משפחה ומשלם הכל אפילו צער *mishum pgam mishpacha umeshalem hakol afilu tza'ar*.
So if all there is is צער *tza'ar*, hit me, you could
be מוחל *Mochel* on the צער *tza'ar*. But if there's something permanent,
then you could try be מוחל *Mochel* on everything and the guy
has to pay everything. He even has to pay the צער *tza'ar*.
You can't say I'm מוחל *Mochel* on the צער *tza'ar*. Once there's
this objective reality of פגם משפחה *pgam mishpacha*, which to me I'm
saying is like an index. It's not you're paying for the פגם
משפחה *pgam mishpacha*. It's a litmus test to the fact that there's
some objective injury here, you know, then then it can't be reframed.
But something that only affects me and doesn't affect anybody else, then
maybe subjectively maybe I can reframe it.
Does פגם משפחה *pgam mishpacha* even on temporary things?
No, that's why the פגם משפחה *pgam mishpacha* explains the ראשי אברים
*rashei evarim* but not the temporary.
But I understand, but I mean there's still there's still פגם משפחה
*pgam mishpacha* meaning...
Yeah, but a brief one. It's not it's not the type of
פגם *pgam* we're talking about. I mean what can I say? If
it's not permanent then there's no lasting פגם *pgam*.
Because when we did פגם
*pgam* also is not like embarrassment. Embarrassment is we were embarrassed about
the event. פגם *pgam* is like right, something that stays, a stigma.
Yes.
Maybe you're imposing some subjective social sensibility to this. A person
may be speak out of pique or out of anguish or something
but no sensible person would want this. So the משפחה *mishpacha* is
evoking that social sensibility.
Right, right, but the question is is that coming to sort of
say that in the end you didn't really want it, or is
it coming to say that therefore right, those are the things I'm
trying to figure out. Or is therefore objectively there's an injury here.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
Okay. determining what's going on here and the
you know and again this person's like the point's that they're embarrassed
but there's a stain, there's something permanent. And רבא says no, it's
because you're not you cannot really redefine or either be really מוחל
it or really redefine when it comes to that type of an
injury. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
has the third has the third explanation about how to explain the
difference between the case of injury, personal injury and destroying a vessel.
רבי יוחנן אמר, יש הן שהוא כלאו ויש לאו שהוא כהן. Rabbi
Yochanan amar yesh hen she-hu ke-lav ve-yesh lav she-hu ke-hen. Sometimes the
no means yes and yes means no. Okay, which basically means, now
I won't tell you רש"י's Rashi read, I'll tell you תוספות's Tosafos?
which is much better. He says if somebody says when the משנה
Mishna says על מנת לפטור, al menas liftor? right, it's like it's
a question. So the other guy says, I say, "blind me." You
say, "על מנת לפטור?" al menas liftor. and I say, "yeah." So
the question is if I said "yeah" like that, sarcastically, clearly I
meant no. If I said, "Yes, you'll be exempt," then I meant
yes. But the משנה Mishna is talking about a statement that's that's
not explicitly sarcastic and not explicitly sincere. Right, but but and therefore
that type of a statement in this case we're going to interpret
a yes under that circumstances to mean a no. If there's any
if there's any doubt what that yes means, it means a no.
Okay, whereas in the case of breaking a vessel, the default of
a it would be the opposite of you know the default of
a no will be a yes. Okay, if you say "break my
vessel" and then you I say "break my vessel," you say "על
מנת לפטור?" al menas liftor, and I say "no." So, you know,
there also it's like I you can imagine that sarcastic, like why
do you think I asked you? על מנת al menas no? No,
I'm not going to whatever. So therefore if there's any doubt, we'll
interpret that no as a yes.
Is that right? So then it would be depending on your inflection?
No, if the
inflection no, no,
no.
If the inflection makes it clear that it's sarcastic or sincere, then
we interpret it what the inflection makes it clear. If there's any
question about what that might have meant, so in the case of
you know the injuring me, a yes will be interpreted as a
no, and in the case of breaking my vessel, a no will
be interpreted as a yes if there's any doubt as to what
it might have meant. Okay,
here you want to take a look at the תוספות? Tosafos. רבי
יוחנן אמר יש לאו שהוא כהן ויש הן שהוא כלאו. Rabbi Yochanan
amar yesh lav she-hu ke-hen ve-yesh hen she-hu ke-lav. לשני מתניתין קשיא.
li-shnei matnitin kasi. מאי שנא רישא ומאי שנא סיפא? mai shna reisha
u-mai shna seifa? So now we're going to skip what רש"י Rashi
says. He says like this, he says ודוחק
הוא. v'dochak hu. It's about the bottom third of תוספות. Tosafot, Line
starts with the words ודוחק הוא v'dochak hu by רש"י. Rashi. אלא
נראה לפרש דנזקי גופו אפילו אמר ליה הן שדומה כאומר בניחותא. ela
nir'eh l'farshesh d'nizkei gufo afilu amar leh hen she-domeh k'omer bi-nichusa. Even
if he says yes
and it seems like it's said as a non-sarcastic, as a sincere
statement, מסתמא בתמיה קאמר. mistama bitmiya kama. Okay, he presumably obviously means
it like sarcastically, ironically. Okay, we'll interpret a yes if there's even
that you know we'll be inclined to interpret a yes in that
case as a no. ובנזקי ממונו אמר ליה לאו ודומה כאומר
בניחותא. u've'nizkei mamono amar leh lav v'domeh k'omer bi-nichusa. If it seems
like he's saying but it's not 100%, מסתמא בתמיה קאמר. mistama bitmiya
kama. We'll interpret that no as a yes. Okay, so let's go
back to the גמרא. Gemara So this is not an absolute like
רבא and the other like the answer about ראשי איברים rashei evarim
and פגם משפחה. Those are saying whatever you're trying to do, objectively
you can never make this any different. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
no, you could always be מוחל one or not מוחל the other,
but we assume that there's a general thing, we assume a general
reality of how people what people mean and therefore we're going to
interpret statements along those lines. Okay, so let's read that again. רבי
יוחנן אמר Rabbi Yochanan amar, יש הן שהוא כלאו ויש לאו שהוא
כהן. yesh hen she-hu ke-lav ve-yesh lav she-hu ke-hen. תניא נמי הכי:
tanya nami hachi: הכני ופצעני, ha-kakeini u-f'tzeni, על מנת לפטור. al menas
liftor, He says on the condition to be
פטור. patur. ואמר לו הן, v'amar lo hen, יש הן שהוא כלאו
yesh hen she-hu ke-lav and
יש הן שהוא yesh hen she-hu ke-no. קרע כסותי, k'ra k'susi, על
מנת לפטור, al menat liftor? ואמר לו לאו, v'amar lo lav, יש
לאו שהוא כהן. yesh lav she-hu ke-hen. That the לאו lav is
going to mean a yes.
Now it doesn't
again, if it's a clear and explicit no, but we'll be but
generally we'll interpret that as a yes. Okay.
שברת
כדי קרעת כסותי
חייב. shevares kadi k'ras k'susi chayav. Break my
vessel, tear my garment, you're חייב. chayav. But if he says על
מנת לפטור, al menat liftor. then you're פטור. ורמינהי, u-remini, I'll ask
you on this. לשמור, lishmor, it says if somebody gives to somebody
something to watch, ולא לאבד, v'lo l'abed, but not if he was
given it to him to destroy. Then he's not obligated to watch
it.
לשמור ולא לקרוע, lishmor v'lo likroa, לשמור ולא לחלק לעניים, lishmor v'lo
l'chalek l'aniyim, not to give it out to the poor. So in
those cases if it was given to you to destroy, you don't
you're not obligated to watch it. Now the גמרא gemara understands if
when I say you "here take this and you can go ahead
and destroy it if you want," that you're not obligated to watch
it, that's only meaningful, that you're exempt of watching it only because
my statement "you can destroy it..." if you want is a meaningful
statement. You really would be allowed to destroy it and not be
liable. So the implication of this is that if I tell you,
take this and you're allowed to destroy it that you'd be exempt
for destroying it. How's that different from our משנה mishna where in
our משנה mishna I have to explicitly say על מנת לפטור? al
menat liftor? And here you don't have to say על מנת לפטור.
al menat liftor, So אמר רב הונא לא קשיא, amar Rav Huna
lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא דאתו לידיה הא דלא אתו לידיה.
ha de'atu lideih ha delo atu lideih. If actually I give it
to you and then I say, you know, you can go ahead
and destroy it once you took possession of it, you know, or
in the time while you were taking possession of it or after
you took possession of it, then you become more responsible for it.
And then I have to explicitly exempt you. But if you haven't
taken possession of it yet and I say, oh, you see my
shirt over there? You can go ahead and you know, go ahead
and take it and you can destroy it. So since you haven't
taken it yet and assumed any responsibility yet, so then your whole
then you're allowed to go ahead and destroy it without any even
without me explicitly exempting you.
And I actually give it to you and
say you can destroy it.
I know, I know. I understand.
Let's see how the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר ליה רבא לשמור דאתו
לידיה משמע. lishmor de'atu lideih mashma. No, it says if you give
it to watch, it sounds like you have actually physically given it
over and you don't have to explicitly exempt him. If you just
say that you can destroy it, he can destroy it. אלא אמר
רבא ella amar Rava הא והא דאתו לידיה. ha veha de'atu lideih.
They both came into his hands. ולא קשיא. velo kashya. הא דאתו
לידיה בתורת שמירה הא דאתו לידיה בתורת קריעה. ha de'atu lideih betorat
shemira ha de'atu lideih betorat kria. That makes sense. If as I'm
giving it to you I say, Michael, here, you know, take this
and you can go ahead and destroy it, then it's given to
him in the context of something he should be destroying. So there's
no liability. If I give it to him and I say, by
the way, Michael, that thing of mine that you've been watching, please
you can go ahead and destroy, so then he already assumed responsibility
to watch it. I need to be more explicit that I'm exempting
him here and I have to say that you could be exempt.
Now by the way תוספות, Tosafot because this whole thing is so
bizarre if I'm saying explicitly please destroy it, why do you have
to say that you're exempting him? תוספות Tosafot tries to reframe it
a little, like I didn't say please destroy it, I said you
can destroy it if you want. And therefore maybe the reason I'm
saying that is so Michael shouldn't feel like I don't want to
watch those things, he's gonna any type of little thing is going
to happen to it, he's going to make me pay. I said
you know what Michael, it doesn't matter even if you destroy it,
it would be okay with me. But it's not but it's not
really okay with me. I'm just saying that to make him... so
תוספות Tosfos again reframes that that's what you're saying because otherwise it
would seem if you explicitly tell somebody to destroy it, well, you
know, why would you have to
say על מנת לפטור? Okay, now the גמרא Gemara ends this.
It's really
with this
to have lawyers in exactly. ההוא ארנקי hahu arneki דצדקה דאתי לפומבדיתא.
de-tzedaka de-ata le-Pumbedita. So there was a wallet, a pouch filled of
צדקה tzedaka money that came to פומבדיתא Pumbedita to be distributed to
the poor. אפקדיה רב יוסף גבי ההוא גברא. afkedih Rav Yosef gabei
hahu gavra. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef gave it over to a
certain person to distribute. פשע בה, pasha bah, he was negligent. גנבו
גנבי, ganvu ganvei, and it was stolen. Oh, אתו גנבי גנבוה, atu
ganvei ganvuha, thieves came, they stole it. חייביה רב יוסף, chiyveih Rav
Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef said you gotta now pay back
all the money that was stolen. אמר ליה אביי והתניא amar leh
Abaye vehatanya לשמור ולא לחלק לעניים? lishmor velo lechalek la'aniyim? If money
is given to you to distribute to the needs, you're exempt. Why?
Because as soon as I give you money to distribute to the
עניים, aniyim, Michael, here, here's twenty dollars I'm giving to צדקה, tzedaka,
please give it to the עניים, aniyim, it's no longer mine. I've
given it over to צדקה. tzedaka. So if Michael loses it, who's
going to bring him to a דין תורה? din torah? So why
isn't so that's why even if it's given over לחלק לעניים, lechalek
la'aniyim, you know, it falls between the cracks. You're exempt from liability.
So why here is he liable? אמר ליה עניי דפומבדיתא מיקץ קייצי
להו ולישמור הוא. amar leh aniyey de-Pumbedita mikatz kaitzi lehu u-lishmor hu.
No, the עניים aniyim of פומבדיתא Pumbedita they have a fixed amount.
Like they know that they get like every the עניים aniyim get
like, you know, five dollars a day. So therefore, we have a
thousand עניים, aniyim, each one of them it's sort of like welfare
checks or whatever. Each one of them gets a fixed amount, five
dollars a day. So every one of them can bring Michael to
a דין תורה, din torah, right? He who says that was my
five dollars. You know, it was my five dollars. By giving it
over to somebody for the עניים, aniyim, it's like that money is
already clearly defined of how much each עני ani has.
Does he actually tell him it's for the עניים? aniyim? I don't
see here any indication that he actually told him.
No, it seems like that was obviously the context.
Yes. So let's say he didn't tell him,
then it would be right? Yeah, then that could change it. Okay,
הדרן עלך החובל. hadran alach ha-chovel. So that was the end of
החובל. ha-chovel. It's very interesting that this whole פרק perek about personal
injury interrupts the seventh and the ninth and the tenth because the
seventh was about גניבה, geneiva, ninth and the tenth is about גזילה,
gezeila, and you have the personal injury one in the middle, which
is strange because you would think גניבה geneiva and גזילה gezeila and
we're going to see the first משנה mishna is going to deal
with very similar issues. But anyway, I don't know. But חנן, Chanan,
you had a question?
Kafka gave Max Brod all his letters and said, "Please destroy them."
Obviously he would על מנת לפטור, right? I want when I die.
And then he didn't destroy them and he not only did
he publish them.
Right.
But Kafka I'm sure was sincere, but there he just so that's
a nice example, that's true. I remember reading about that.
Yeah, so as
opposed to why does it interrupt... I
the only thing I'll suggest about that is that גניבה, geneivah, we
tend to forget this because the גמרא Gemara focuses on the object,
on the payment, but the classic גניבה geneivah is burglary as you
enter into somebody's house, right? And therefore and those are classic cases
in the Torah also that could lead to murder, standing injuries, standing
up for
yourself, killing the guy who's breaking into your home and so on.
So it could be that as opposed to גזילה's gezeilah just all
about the object. Here there may be a, although again sometimes mugging
people are also killed in a mugging or somehow. But there seems
to be something more about personal intrusion, a violation. People whose homes
have been broken in, I think it takes much more longer to
recover than somebody who's been mugged if they haven't been physically injured.
So there is that sense of violation and entering, intrusion onto me,
my house is an extension of me. So that's maybe why חבלה
chavalah follows it and then you have גזילה. gezeilah. Although still you
would have imagined there would have been a hierarchy: do חבלה chavalah
and then גניבה geneivah and then גזילה, gezeilah, or גזילה gezeilah then
גניבה geneivah then חבלה. chavalah. It's still interesting the interruption. Anyway, let's
take a look now as we turn to the last two פרקים
prakim that deal with גזילה. gezeilah. הגוזל עצים ועשאן כלים, hagozel eitzin
ve'asa'an keilim, צ"ג עמוד ב'. tzadik gimmel amud bet. Somebody who steals
wood and turns them into some type of a utensil. It's so
funny whenever we did this seventh פרק perek I kept on having
to say burgles, who burgles this, burgles this, which is a word,
it's a verb, who ever uses that in normal English? Anyway, here
I can finally say steals, but I was looking at the Soncino
and Soncino translates גזילה gezeilah throughout this פרק perek as misappropriates,
which that is what it is, but normally we use that for
more white-collar crime. But anyway, okay, הגוזל עצים hagozel eitzin if somebody
steals wood ועשאן כלים ve'asa'an keilim and turns them into some type
of a utensil. צמר ועשאן בגדים, tzemer ve'asa'an begadim, wool and makes
them into clothes. Makes a שינוי, shinui, right? משלם כשעת הגזילה. meshalem
kishat hagezeilah. So the owner can't say, oh thank you very much,
I'll just take this nice new garment that you wove. No, actually
I now, the גזלן gazlan now owns the garment and I'll just
pay you the cost of the thing when I stole it because
that's the principle of שינוי קונה, shinui koneh, change makes me own
it.
גוזל פרה מעוברת וילדה, gozel parah me'uberet veyalada, if he stole a
pregnant cow and it then gave birth. רחל טעונה וגזזה, rachel te'unah
vegazezah, or a sheep that was filled with wool and he sheared
it. משלם דמי פרה העומדת לילד ודמי רחל העומדת ליגזז. meshalem dmei
parah ha'omedet leiled udmei rachel ha'omedet ligazez. So there he owns now
the, it sounds like he owns the baby calf and he owns
the wool. He made a שינוי shinui in those. Those belong to
him. He gives back the non-pregnant cow and the sheared sheep. And
so what does he have to pay? So it says משלם דמי
פרה העומדת לילד ודמי רחל העומדת ליגזז. meshalem dmei parah ha'omedet leiled
udmei rachel ha'omedet ligazez. He pays for a cow that's ready to
give birth and a sheep that is ready to be shorn. Now
it's not clear, does he keep the cow as well? Is the
fact that the cow has given birth a שינוי shinui in the
cow? Is the fact that the sheep has been shorn a שינוי
shinui in the sheep? You wouldn't think so. So what you really
are paying would be the difference. You give back the cow and
then you pay the difference between this cow and one that was
ready to give birth, between this sheep and one that was ready
to be shorn. The משנה's mishnah not so clear, right? The משנה
mishnah says you pay for it as it was בשעת הגזילה. beshat
hagezeilah. So clearly it seems like you own the calf and the
wool. Whether you own the cow or the sheep is a little
ambiguous in the
משנה. mishnah. גוזל פרה ונתעברה אצלו וילדה רחל ונתענה אצלו וגזזה. gozel
parah venit'abra etzlo veyalada rachel venit'ana etzlo vegazezah. Now let's say he
went through the whole cycle: he stole it, it became pregnant then
gave birth, it got wool then he sheared it. In that case
משלם כשעת הגזילה. meshalem kishat hagezeilah. So you again, you keep the
profit you made off it as the גזלן. gazlan. It doesn't seem
so fair, the גזלן gazlan making a profit off of somebody else's
property, but these are the principles that he's קונה koneh with a
שינוי. shinui. He's קונה koneh the new stuff that grew etc. And
in that case he pays the,
he just gives back the sheep and the
cow. Okay, or now זה הכלל כל הגזלנין משלמין כשעת הגזילה. zeh
haklal kol hagazlanin meshalmin kishat hagezeilah. You pay as it was when
you stole it, not for anything different. Now of course what the
משנה mishnah should have said is, you know what the case that's
missing from the משנה mishnah is that you stole a sheep that
was shorn and it got wool and then it came time to
pay it back, right? So what would you think in that case?
Could I say okay, I stole your sheep, it had been sheared,
I kept it by me, now it's filled with wool. I'm the
sheep. Michael, here's your sheep back, but it's worth 500 dollars more,
could you give me the 500
bucks, right? So there the answer would be no, it's not a
שינוי, shinui, I'm not קונה koneh it, but it should have given
that example because the משנה mishnah said משלם כשעת הגזילה. meshalem kishat
hagezeilah. There actually will be a time where effectively you'll be משלם
meshalem more than שעת הגזילה shat hagezeilah when the thing improved without
a שינוי, shinui, right? When the cow, I stole the cow and
it became pregnant, now I have to give you back a pregnant
cow, I'm actually giving you
back.
If he shears the sheep and then gives it back, he can
keep the shearings?
If he shears the sheep and then gives it back.
If he shears the sheep and gives it back.
He stole the—yes, that’s a case in the משנה. Mishna. He stole
the sheep that was—he stole the sheep that was without shearings, it
became, it got wool and then he sheared it. Right, then he
keeps the shearings. Yes, that’s a case in the משנה. Mishna. Okay,
so now the גמרא says like this: אמרי עצים ועשאן כלים Amri
eitzim va’asaan keilim אין, in, it sounds like it’s only a שינוי
shinuy when you actually turn them into some type of a—of an
implement. My whole life I’ve been translating כלים keilim as vessel, but
I’ve been told that vessel sounds like the—like something you eat from,
you know, so I’ve been looking at other translations of it like
instrument. I think implement is probably the best. Implement is more generic.
Okay, anyway, so it sounds like only when you make something into
some type of an implement, like it gets to a certain stage
of change. שיפן shiphan לא, lo, but if you simply sanded it,
you know, and—what—what’s it called when you do a—not sanding, planed it
or something, it would—that would not be enough. צמר ועשאן בגדים tzemer
va’asaan begadim אין, in, wool when you make it into clothes, that’s
a שינוי, shinuy, but it sounds like לבנן libnan לא, if you
only whitened the wool, which is after shearing the wool you basically,
you know, clean it and rub it and then it, you know,
becomes nice and bright and white. So that would not be enough.
That’s not enough of a שינוי. shinuy. רמינהי, remi’nei, I’ll ask you
on this. We have a ברייתא. braita, גזל עצים ושיפן, gezal eitzim
v’shiphan, it speaks about an earlier stage. If you stole wood and
you planed it. אבנים וסיתתן, avanim v’sitatan, you stole stones and
you—whatever also, what’s it called, chiseled them or something. צמר ולבנן, tzemer
v’libnan, wool and you whitened it. פשתן ונקאן, pishtan v’nika’an, flax that
you cleaned, you know, you combed it or whatever from the raw
stage. משלם כשעת הגזלה, meshaleim k’sha’at hagezeilah, you pay—you also you own
it now and you only pay like you stole it. So why
does our משנה Mishna talk about a later stage? It sounds like
even an earlier stage.
אמר אביי, amar Abaye, said אביי, Abaye,
תנא דידן קתני שינוי דרבנן דהדרא. tana didan katani shinuy de’rabbanan de’hadra.
Our—now you would think of course that our משנה Mishna is the
more drastic שינוי, shinuy, right? Which אביי Abaye is going to re-read
the case in our משנה Mishna that our משנה Mishna is the
less significant שינוי. shinuy. Our משנה Mishna is talking about a more
minor שינוי shinuy which is only rabbinic, that it’s considered that the
גזלן gazlan owns it only rabbinically, because it’s a type of a
שינוי דהדרא, shinuy de’hadra, which is שינוי החוזר. shinuy hachozeir. It’s a
שינוי shinuy that could be reverted back to the original state. No,
no, no—well let’s take a look.
וכל שכן שינוי דאורייתא, v’chol shekein shinuy d’oraita, and certainly a biblical
שינוי, shinuy, which is something that does not revert. How is it
that our משנה Mishna is a lesser שינוי? shinuy? עצים ועשאן כלים
בעצים משופים. eitzim va’asaan keilim b’eitzim meshupim. The case about making some
type of an implement with wood, that’s when you stole already planed
wood, already, you know, smoothed wood. ומאי ניהו נסרים, umai nihu nesarim,
and what—beams. And you stole some beams. And what did—beams, and what
do you do with the beams? You went to Home Depot, you
took some nice smoothed-out cut beams and you just put them on
your roof top. You didn’t put any plaster, you didn’t put any
nails. I guess—that’s not exactly a vessel. You’d have to think of
some other way where you fitted some beams together without any nails
and in some type of a way that you could just undo
it.
Okay, but like by the way stones, you know, we were talking
about this once in שיעור, shiur, how there was like this, you
know, there’s this ancient, you know, wisdom or—whatever, you know, skill of
being able to make these stone walls without any plaster, without any
other material, and they’ve lasted for like hundreds of years, you know,
or even longer. So anyway, so there’s ways of making something without
making any change to the object. What?
Apparently a typical life expectancy is like 250 years. Where? And then
they fall apart.
Oh, then they just collapse. Interesting. Okay, so—so בעצים
משופים ומאי ניהו נסרים דשינוי דהדרא לבי אצלו, b’eitzim meshupim umai nihu
nesarim de’shinuy de’hadra l’vei atzlo, it could be reverting to its original
state, דאי בעי משלף להו, de’ee ba’ei mishlaf lehu, you could just,
you know, extract it, pull it out. צמר ועשאן בגדים בצמר טווי,
tzemer va’asaan begadim b’tzemer tavi, so how does wool—that you made into
clothes? It’s already wool that’s been twisted, woven. You basically didn’t steal
wool, you stole yarn. Okay, if you stole yarn and you knitted
something, you could always, you know, undo what you’ve knitted. Right, I
mean I guess, take my כיפה kippah here and completely undo it
and get back some strings. Okay, theoretically that’s possible.
דשינוי
דהדרא לבי אצלו. de’shinuy de’hadra l’vei atzlo.
Taking a, you know, piece of metal and putting it on as
my roof.
Right, right. I mean you did something, you did change it, which
is why—but it’s a change that with enough effort can go back
to the original state. דאי בעי סתר ליה, de’ee ba’ei satar lei,
if you want you can undo your whole nice Afghan and get
back all the nice yarn. Okay, וכל שכן שינוי דאורייתא, v’chol shekein
shinuy d’oraita, certainly a biblical שינוי. shinuy. דתנא ברא שינוי דאורייתא קתני
שינוי דרבנן לא קתני. de’tana bara shinuy d’oraita katani שינוי דרבנן לא
קתני shinuy de’rabbanan lo katani. The external תנא, tana, the ברייתא, Braita.
is talking about a biblical one. He’s talking about—so what we thought
was less, he actually says is more. No, when you plane the
wood or when you carve the stone, you can’t—you can’t change that
back, so that’s an even more bigger שינוי. shinuy. Anyway, okay, now
by the way, this idea that that carving the to plane the
woods would be, sounds like it would be sufficient by itself because
it's a physical change that doesn't revert, תוספות Tosfos importantly limits it.
תוספות Tosfos, says, if you take a look at תוספות, Tosfos?
where's
תוספות? Tosfos. we'll read the next line and then we'll see the
תוספות. Tosfos So the גמרא says like this, רב אשי אמר, Rav
Ashi amar, רב אשי Rav Ashi says, תנא דידן נמי שינוי דאורייתא
קתני. Tanna didan nami shinuy d'Oraita ktani. No, even in our משנה,
Mishnah, even though he agrees with אביי's Abaye type of description, he
says it's also a biblical change. Why? דאורייתא קתני ושינוי דרבנן לא
קתני. d'Oraita ktani v'shinuy d'rabbanan lo ktani. תנא דידן נמי שינוי דאורייתא
קתני. Tanna didan nami shinuy d'Oraita ktani. עצים ועשאן כלים. Etzim v'asan
kelim. What does it mean when you took a wood and you
made it into a vessel? It means the exact same thing as
the ברייתא. Braita, It means that you planed it but you did
nothing more. It says בוכני, bukhni, like a type of a pestle,
which is the one that you do the banging with, the mortar
or the pestle? I think the pestle you do the banging with.
Anyway, okay, the pestle is pounding.
I don't know, and some type of a pounder, okay, דהיינו שיפן.
d'hainu shifan. So when the משנה Mishnah says כלים, kelim, it doesn't
mean some complicated thing with nails and cutting, it is the case
of the ברייתא, Braita. you smoothed it out and now you can
use it as a vessel. Okay, it's the exact same case as
the ברייתא. Braita צמר ועשאן
בגדים, Tzemer v'asan begadim, wool that you made into clothes, נמטי, namti,
that's talking about felt, דהיינו שינוי דלא הדר. d'hainu shinuy d'lo hadar.
So you did not make it into, you didn't do the whole
thing that the ברייתא Braita talked about about whitening it or whatever,
you did some type of a thing which it's אינו חוזר, eino
chozer, which didn't require the middle steps of the process. But it's
a שינוי שאינו חוזר. shinuy she'eino chozer. Okay, and הליבון, halibun, okay,
so that's the end. Now by the way, תוספות Tosfos says, עצים
ועשאן, Etzim v'asan, now תוספות Tosfos says this important point because what
he says is the smoothing is a case you made it into
a vessel. So תוספות Tosfos, says that's an important limitation on the
idea of the smoothing and the planing. If you look at תוספות,
Tosafot's עצים ועשאן כלים בוכני דאיירי בשיפוי כי האי, Etzim v'asan kelim
bukhni d'airi b'shifuy ki hai, only a type of a planing like
this, שנעשה בכך בוכני, she'na'aseh b'kach bukhni, that was made into a
pounder, מועיל. mo'il. That would be a שינוי shinuy that doesn't reverse
and that allows you to be קונה. koneh. דחשיב שינוי מעשה וכן
עבדי נסרי נמי מהני. d'chashiv shinuy ma'aseh v'chen ovdey nisari nami mahani.
Or if you made it into like planks of wood, you took
just a piece of lumber and you made it into a beam.
But it has to be, it doesn't have to be, it has
to be something that it has a different identity. It's not enough,
what did you
do to it?
What? What do you mean what did you do to it? You
took some unshaped piece of lumber and you made it into a
nice
two-by-four. Okay, so you cut it, you planed it, okay, אבל שיפוי
שאין משתנה שמו בכך, aval shifuy she'ein mishtaneh shmo b'kach, if you
just like took something that was rough and you took it into
your woodshop and you sandpapered it and smoothed it or whatever, so
before you had a rough beam and now you have a smooth
beam, okay, לא מהני. lo mahani. וכן אמרינן לקמן, v'chen amrinan l'kamman,
גזל דקלא וקטליה, gazal dikla v'katlei, if somebody stole a palm tree
and cut it down, לא קני. lo kani. דקלא ועבדיה גובי לא
קני, dikla v'avdeh guvi lo kani, or even if you had a
palm tree and you made it like into like planks, דגובי דדקלא
מיקרי, d'guvi d'dikla mikrei, because it still has the same name. So
this is a really important idea. Don't think that any physical change,
even if it cannot be reversed, is all of a sudden called
a שינוי. shinuy. Right, let's say I steal Michael's car and I
take my key and I scratch, you know, and I scratch some
part, you know, something, well it's not חוזר, chozer, I don't know,
maybe if you have a good enough mechanic or something. But I
do some type of a thing that doesn't change, is it oh
שינוי shinuy is קונה. koneh. Okay, not every physical change that's אינו
חוזר eino chozer means that it's a new identity to the object.
So that's an important limitation on this idea. Okay, let's continue now.
So the גמרא now moves on to the next stage. והליבון מי
הוי שינוי? V'halibun mi havei shinuy? Now the ברייתא braita says that
whitening the, the, the wool is a שינוי. shinuy. Now you understand
whitening doesn't mean you pour white dye on it, wool is white,
but it means, you know, when it's originally shaved from the sheep,
it's very dirty and whatever, you know, it's been out, so you
have to wash and comb and you know, whatever, and bang it.
It's a whole process and then it's really nice and bright and
white. Okay, so let's take a look. והליבון מי הוי שינוי? V'halibun
mi havei shinuy? Is that really a שינוי? shinuy? ורמינהי, V'reminhi, לא
הספיק ליתנו לו עד שצבעו פטור. lo hispik litno lo ad shetzva'o
patur. So we have a case
where, hold on, let me just check רש״י Rashi about this. Right,
just a
sec. Okay, so a case of ראשית הגז. reishis hageiz. So when
you shear your sheep, okay, every year you shear your sheep, okay,
if you have five sheep that you've sheared and they produce a
certain amount of wool, then you have to give from that, those
shearings a certain amount to the כהן, kohen, it's not a fixed
amount, but a certain amount, sort of like תרומה, trumah, it can't
be a trivial amount but you give something to the כהן, kohen,
but it has to be five sheep that produce a certain amount
of wool. Now let's say before you got around, you sheared the
sheep, okay, and you were obligated to give something to the כהן,
kohen, but before you did, you whitened the wool. Is it now
something different and no longer the wool that you sheared and now
you don't have to give the gift to the כהן? kohen? That's
the question. Okay, so. לא הספיק ליתנו לו עד שצבעו, Lo hispik
litno lo ad shetzeva'o, you didn't have a chance to give to
the כהן kohen until you whitened it,
I'm sorry, that's if you until I said that wrong. If you
until you colored it, until you dyed it, excuse me, then you're
exempt, then it's something different, then it's a שינוי. shinui. לובנו ולא
צבעו, Livno velo tzeva'o, if you just whitened it and you did
not dye it, חייב. chayav. So you see there that whitening is
not a שינוי shinui and our ברייתא braita assumes whitening is a
שינוי. shinui. What's the answer? So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, לא קשיא,
lo kashya, it's not difficult, הא רבי שמעון הא רבנן, Ha Rabbi
Shimon Ha Rabbanan, it's a debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and
רבנן, דתניא. גזזה, Gzezaho,
צבעה, tzeva'o, וארגה, ve'argo, again with this case of shearing the sheep,
this is a slightly different scenario. It's that you sheared one sheep
and you did something to the wool and then you sheared the
other sheep, so the amount of wool that you sheared from the
first sheep does not combine to make the total amount that would
make you obligated to give it, okay? So you sheared one
sheep, you spun the wool and you wove it, אין מצטרף, ein
mitztaref, it doesn't combine with the shearings of the other sheep to
obligate you in ראשית הגז. reishis hagez. לובנו, Luvno, if you whitened
it, רבי שמעון אומר אין מצטרף וחכמים אומרים מצטרף. Rabbi Shimon omer
ein mitztaref veChachamim omrim mitztaref. It's a debate. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says it doesn't combine and the חכמים Chachamim say it does combine.
So you show there's one ברייתא says ליבון libun is a שינוי
shinui by stealing, one says it's not by ראשית הגז. reishis hagez.
It's a debate of תנאים, Tannaim, how much is this considered a
change, and what's the debate? Presumably, you can't, you can't revert it
to its original state, but this seems to be תוספות question. Of
course, you did a physical change that's not revertible, but does it
change its identity? Does it go from being raw wool to being
wool? You know, how much is that now thing a change of
identity seems to be the question. Okay? So he says it's a
מחלוקת. machlokes. We'll read one more line and we'll end for here
today.
רבא אמר הא והא רבי שמעון ולא קשיא. Rava amar ha veha
Rabbi Shimon velo kashya. It could both be רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
that says that ליבון libun is a change, but there are different
degrees of ליבון. libun. One is a case where you just like
sort of combed it out with your hand, הא דנפציה נפצי, ha
denaftzei naftzei, and the other is where you did the process with
like a comb, you know, הא דסרקה סרקי, ha desarkeh sarki, it's
a much more vigorous process and maybe a much more drastic change.
So there are different degrees. רב חייא בר אבין אמר, Rav Chiya
bar Avin amar, הא דחורי חיוורא, ha dechorei chivra, one is that
you just washed it, הא דחורי חיוורא דגופריתא, ha dechorei chivra degufrisa,
the other is you used some sulfur to whiten it, so that
was more of a change. Okay? So that's basically different answers, either
there's a debate whether it is a change or different degrees of
whitening it, some could be considered a change and some not. So
we'll pick up with this tomorrow.
And as usual, the זמנים, zmanim, Stone's hours, everyone do it by
hand or by.